Bertha C. Reynolds Papers, 1907-1994
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Bertha Capen Reynolds papers
1907-1994
1925-1979
Reynolds, Bertha Capen, 1885-
MS 128
22 boxes, 2 volumes, microfilm (8.75 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Social worker and professor. Reynolds' professional career is well documented, including her years as associate director of the Smith College School for Social Work; as case supervisor at National Maritime Union; and as a teacher of social work. She also published numerous texts on the practice of social work. Material includes correspondence, published and unpublished writings, lectures, oral histories, and memorabilia.
by Rachel A. Levine Literary Executor
It is thanks to the Centennial Committee of a small core of professional colleagues convened by Jack Kamaiko; to Vida S. Grayson, oral historian, Smith College School for Social Work; and to Dorothy Green, research associate, and Susan Grigg, director, Sophia Smith Collection, that Bertha Capen Reynolds and her writings are being resurrected from virtual oblivion. The centennial programs are to commemorate her birth and her achievements as scholar, teacher, and writer like no other; and to introduce recent generations of students and practitioners, and those to follow, to her rich, thought-provoking, trail? blazing contributions to the social work literature and to the teaching and practice of social work. It would be logical for these people to ask, as some have, why they had not known about so eminent a person during the course of their education and training.
In historical perspective, reasons tend to become obscured or rationalized; but stripped to raw essence, it is for the reason that for the later period of her productive years a conspiracy of silent ostracism, not unlike a gentlemen's agreement, prevailed among the established leadership in the profession and among the prestigious schools of social work and social agencies; and her writings were omitted from the reading lists of schools of social work. The consequences were two-fold: the loss to students of original and stimulating learning materials; and the loss to Bertha C. Reynolds of her lifeline to all levels of contacts that she characterized as "nourishing," as well as the loss of the means of earning a livelihood.
Because such a phenomenon had not occurred in the profession before Bertha C. Reynolds's time and has not occurred since, as far as I know, an explanation is in order. Her writings trace the historical events and the process which brought her to self-liberation from the constraints of time-honored doctrine.
She believed that catastrophes like war, cyclic economic depression, chronic poverty, hunger, and a host of others, and their effects upon the human condition, and on a global scale, are but the symptoms of underlying causes which are rooted in societal values and systems; therefore, the searchlight should be beamed on, and work directed to, the elimination of the causes. Moreover, social work, the profession most intimately knowledgeable about the tolls of such disasters in human misery, and deeply involved in its alleviation, has a role in helping to change value systems in a society which tolerates the degradation of body and spirit of masses of humanity. These principles were (and still are) in sharp contrast to those held acceptable by individuals and groups in power. But what "cooked her goose," to quote a phrase, was that she used Marxist ideology as a frame of reference for her beliefs and its science of society as the key to the solution of such widespread socio-economic-political disasters. And, she dared to present her views in public! Yet paradoxical as it may seem, her abiding faith in her beloved America, and in its people, and in the profession, to show the way to the changes needed for a better world for all peoples, never wavered. "This book is dedicated to an unbreakable tie with the interests of humanity" is the dedication in her book, Social Work and Social Living.
The legacy of the writings of Bertha C. Reynolds to her profession contains searching questions and insightful, incisive answers which are as relevant, if not more so, to today's world as when they were written. Is this legacy worth her sacrifices of creature comforts and of the acclaim which undoubtedly would have been hers had she made compromises to conformity; will it enlighten and inspire others to creative thinking, and to the courage to speak out for infusion of new ideas, without which a profession remains static? I asked her several months before her death, what message would she send to young people entering the profession today? Her response was, "Do not get locked into traditional molds."
Bertha C. Reynolds's writings attest to the wisdom in the Confucian saying, in paraphrase: to understand the present and the future, one must study and know the past. The inference is that the past is a harbinger of the present and the future, the three being linked in a continuum. Judgments as to the veracity of this linkage and its manifestations (as her writings indicate) will no doubt vary when examined in the light of the contemporary American and world scene. But beyond doubt is the rare treat which is in store for those who study her writings for the first time.
February 1985
Bertha C. Reynolds was a pioneer educator and practitioner in the field of social work and an innovative writer on broader social subjects. These are some principal events in her personal and professional life:
1885 born in Brockton, Massachusetts, on December 11 to Mary (Capen) Reynolds (1853-1947) and Franklin Stewart Reynolds (1853-1887).
1889 moved to the Capen family farm in Stoughton, Massachusetts, after her father's death.
1897 entered school for the first time after home tutoring by her mother.
1904-08 attended Smith College with support of her aunt, Bessie T. Capen, principal of the Capen (later Burnham) School in Northampton; graduated Phi Beta Kappa.
1909-11 taught in the high school department of Atlanta University; left because of ill health.
1912 had brief psychotherapy with James J. Putnam, M.D.
1912-13 enrolled in the Boston School for Social Workers (later the Simmons College School of Social Work).
1913-18 employed as caseworker for the Boston Children's Aid Society.
1914 received B.S. degree from Simmons at the end of one year's employment as a social worker.
1918 participated in the first course in psychiatric social work at Boston Psychopathic Hospital under Elmer E. Southard and Mary C. Jarrett. completed the first Smith College summer session for social workers, the Training School for Psychiatric Social Work (which later became the Smith College School for Social Work), established to train workers to rehabilitate shell-shocked soldiers.
1919 publication of a monograph, The Selection of Foster Homes for Children, with Mary S. Doran.
1919-23 worked as director of social services at Danvers State Hospital in Massachusetts.
1923-25 worked in new clinics for behavioral training of pre-school children in the Division of Mental Hygiene in Boston.
1925-35 served as associate director of the Smith College School for Social Work, teaching courses in the summer term and supervising students' field placements during the rest of the year; conducted research and had clinical assignments at the Child Guidance Clinic in Philadelphia and at the Institute for Child Guidance and the Jewish Board of Guardians in New York.
1927-28 began an intensive psychoanalysis with Frankwood E. Williams, M.D.
1930 presented her first major paper, "The Role of the Psychiatric Social Worker in Therapy," at the First International Congress on Mental Hygiene.
1930-67 traveled around the country giving speeches and conducting in-service institutes for social workers.
1931-42 publication of many articles in The Family on casework and the relationship of social work to society.
1932-33 resumed psychoanalysis with Dr. Williams after five-year interval. was a member of the Milford Conference study group and served as committee secretary.
1934 became a member of the advisory council and an important contributor to Social Work Today, a journal of the rank-and-file movement made up mainly of public relief workers who advocated unionization of social workers. publication of Between Client and Community: A Study in Responsibility in Social Case Work.
1935 changed positions at the School for Social Work to become associate director in charge of advanced courses; established and taught the first advanced course, Plan D, for the training of supervisors and teachers of social work.
1937 offered her resignation to Everett Kimball, director of the School for Social Work, due to their disagreement over the direction of the program, her political activities, and the termination of Plan D.
1938 left the School for Social Work after teaching the last group in the Plan D program. publication of "Re-Thinking Social Case Work."
1939-42 self-employed as a consultant in staff development for social work agencies.
1942 publication of her major work for social work educators, Learning and Teaching in the Practice of Social Work, describing the contributions of psychology and the social sciences to the problems of practice and teaching in social work.
1943-47 appointed by the United Seamen's Service to the Personal Service Department of the National Maritime Union, where she became case supervisor.
1948-54 taught a seminar at the William Alanson White Institute in New York on the relationship between social work and psychiatry.
1948 retired to the family home in Stoughton, where she studied Marxist works, corresponded with friends and former students, had a small clinical practice, and worked as a volunteer on community projects, for the Methodist Church, and the Stoughton Historical Society.
1951 publication of Social Work and Social Living, drawing on her National Maritime Union experience.
1963 publication of her autobiography, An Uncharted Journey.
1964 publication of "The Social Casework of an Uncharted Journey" in Social Work.
1964-76 was honored by Boston University; the Adelphi, Columbia, Fordham, Hunter, New York University, and Yeshiva schools of social work; the New York City chapter of the National Association of Social Workers; and the alumni of the Smith College School for Social Work. was honored by the town of Stoughton for participation in community affairs.
Bertha C. Reynolds died at home in Stoughton on October 29, 1978.
The Bertha C. Reynolds Papers consist of correspondence, writings, printed materials, memorabilia, and miscellaneous papers. They are concentrated in the period following Reynolds's appointment as associate director of the Smith College School for Social Work in 1925 and are strongest for her final decades in Stoughton.
The most outstanding segment of the papers is Reynolds's correspondence with her friends and former students. The letters addressed to her are mainly from the 1960s and 1970s, but her own letters include sequences from the 1930s and 1940s (saved by those who received them). This correspondence is distinguished by its long and thoughtful discussions of professional, political, and religious topics as well as by reports on personal activities. The political and religious interests also appear in printed material gathered over the years and in unpublished writings.
Direct documentation of Reynolds's social work teaching and writing is excellent for some kinds of activities and significant for all others. Her work as associate director of the Smith College School for Social Work is represented by correspondence with Director Everett Kimball spanning the entire period and by notes for an alumnae seminar. Many of her lectures and her contributions to institutes, conferences, and seminars are documented by unpublished texts as well as by correspondence and printed materials. The items related to her published writings consist mainly of correspondence and copies of the publications, but there are also a few manuscripts and typescripts. Her work at the National Maritime Union is represented by staff minutes and position papers, printed material, and correspondence following the termination of the program; this section provides the best documentation of her approach to clinical practice. Her independent consultations are documented in such materials as speeches, correspondence, and brochures, but there are no immediate records of this professional work. Many of these activities are also treated in letters to friends and in autobiographical writings.
Other papers document Reynolds's earlier and later years. Her youth is represented by a diary she compiled retrospectively from family letters, by an unpublished autobiography, and by a few of her undergraduate papers. Aside from her retrospective writings, there is nothing for the period between her graduation from Smith in 1908 and her return in 1918. Her final years in Stoughton are well documented in correspondence, writings, and printed materials about her work on behalf of the Stoughton Fair Housing and Human Rights Association, the Stoughton Historical Society, and the Methodist Church; in correspondence and printed material concerning the honors that she received in the 1960s and 1970s; and also in the aforementioned correspondence with friends.
This collection is organized as follows:
I. CORRESPONDENCE
II. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES
III. WRITINGS
IV. SUBJECT FILES
V. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL, PHOTOGRAPHS, and MEMORABILIA
BOOKS ON SHELF
MICROFORMS
ORAL HISTORIES
ADDITIONS TO COLLECTION
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The Bertha C. Reynolds Papers are open for study and research without any special restrictions.
History of the Collection
The greater part of the Bertha C. Reynolds Papers was bequeathed to the Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College, by Bertha C. Reynolds in her will written in 1969. Reynolds transferred some items in 1968; the rest were received after her death, in part through the efforts of Vida S. Grayson, Rachel A. Levine, and Orrin Hansen. These materials have been augmented by gifts of Reynolds's letters and other papers and photographs from Rachel A. Levine, Jack Kamaiko, Eleanor Flexner and Helen Terry, Charlotte and Ray Koch, Ruth Middleman, Clara Rabinowitz, Constance Kyle Lamb, Rose Noble, Tomannie Walker, Ruth Newman Schwarz, Norma and Wesley Stinson, Vivian Pataki, Ruth Harper, Tessie Berkman (via Devora Schwebel), Fay Goleman, and the Stoughton Historical Society.
Search Terms
Jarrett, Mary C. (Mary Cromwell); Kimball, Everett, 1873-; Reynolds, Bertha Capen, 1885-; Southard, Elmer Ernest, 1876-1920; William Alanson White Institute; Psychiatric social work--United States--History--Sources; Smith College. School for Social Work--Administration--History--Sources; Social case work--United States--History--Sources; Social work education--United States--History--Sources; Social workers--United States--History--Sources
Additional Information
Related Material
Related materials can be found in the Smith College Archives. Oral histories of social workers conducted by Bertha C. Reynolds are in the Social Work Archive, Sophia Smith Collection. The American Institute of Marxist Studies in New York has Reynolds's bequest of her unpublished writings on Marxist themes. The Stoughton Historical Society has Reynolds and Capen family papers, photographs, and memorabilia.
- Series I. CORRESPONDENCE 1933-1978, 1.0 linear ft.
  This series has three sections: Individual Correspondence: Incoming; Individual Correspondence: Outgoing; and Miscellaneous Correspondence. Other letters are filed according to subject in other series.
  Individual Correspondence consists mainly of letters exchanged between Bertha Reynolds and her friends and former students. All the letters have been arranged according to the name of Reynolds's correspondent.
  Miscellaneous Correspondence is arranged by subject. The folders on "Religion" include exchanges with Dale White and Wesley Stinson, ministers of the Stoughton Methodist Church.
- Series II. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES 1919-1975, .75 linear ft.
  This series has six sections: Danvers State Hospital; Smith College School for Social Work; Institute for Child Guidance; National Maritime Union; William Alanson White Institute; and Speeches, Institutes, Seminars.
  The first section contains case studies used at Danvers State Hospital.
  Reynolds's work at the Smith College School for Social Work is represented by papers related to a seminar for alumnae, correspondence with Everett Kimball, and two case histories probably used for teaching. Additional documentation of Plan D can be found in the Smith College Archives.
  Institute for Child Guidance has a very small amount of descriptive material about the organization, and the proposal and notes for the final report of a study by Reynolds about adolescent girls in a Harlem school. Her letter of appointment to the institute is also included in this folder.
  The papers in the National Maritime Union section consist of minutes of some staff meetings, staff papers on policy matters, and some general descriptive material. A letter in the United Seaman's Service folder (Reynolds being their representative to the NMU) describes her work in detail.
  The seminar taught by Reynolds at the William Alanson White Institute in New York is described in a bulletin. There is also correspondence about her appointment and work at the institute.
  Speeches, Institutes, Seminars contains, in chronological order, texts or notes of most of the speeches given by Reynolds and some routine correspondence; there are also programs, reprints, session transcripts or notes, and correspondence for most of the institutes and seminars that Reynolds gave or participated in from 1929 to 1975 and a text that she used in a debate in 1919.
- Series III. WRITINGS 1918-1975, 2.25 linear ft.
  This series is divided into Correspondence about Publications and Published and Unpublished Works.
  Correspondence about Publications consists mainly of letters exchanged with the group of friends who organized themselves into the Publication Committee for her autobiography, An Uncharted Journey. The rest of this section, arranged by title of the work, consists mostly of routine communications with editors and publishers.
  Unless otherwise noted, Published Works contains only writings in their final printed form.
  Unpublished Works consists of the "Informal Autobiography," Reynolds's annual greeting in verse, and writings on religion and other personal subjects written mostly in her retirement years.
- Series IV. SUBJECT FILES 1922-1979, 1.0 linear ft.
  This series contains materials collected by Bertha Reynolds. The first section, Organizations, consists almost entirely of printed materials of professional associations, unions, and organizations for political and social action. There is a completed form about her history in the Communist party in the folder on that organization. The second section, Miscellaneous, consists mostly of printed materials spanning many of Reynolds's interests plus a transcript of a case history (not by Reynolds) and a typewritten memoir of an unidentified survivor of the Holocaust.
- Series V. BIOGRAPHICAL MATERIAL, PHOTOGRAPHS, AND MEMORABILIA 1907-1979, 1.75 linear ft.
  The first section, Biographical Material, consists of biographical articles, obituaries, and diaries; Smith College undergraduate papers and alumnae materials; correspondence, notes, and printed materials documenting Reynolds's work on behalf of the Stoughton Fair Housing and Human Rights Association, the Stoughton Historical Society, and the First Methodist Church in Stoughton; miscellaneous papers about Reynolds's life in Stoughton; and correspondence and printed materials, including testimonies by leading social workers related to honors and tributes. The second section, Photographs, contains a small number of photographs of Reynolds and others taken from 1925 to 1979. Memorabilia contains a plaque from the Stoughton community, books and papers given by friends, sometimes with inscriptions, and a family history by her brother Frank W. Reynolds.
  [See also Additions to Collection and Oral Histories at the end of Container List]
- Series I. CORRESPONDENCE 1933-1978
  - Individual Correspondence: Incoming
    - A-J, 1951, 1971-78 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - M-W, 1961-76 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Arrington, Winifred, 1969-72 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Deschin, Celia, 1964-70, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Eden, Marilyn, 1971-73 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Engel, Judith, 1968-74, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Flexner, Eleanor, and Helen Terry, 1961-73, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Glass, Robert, 1966-72, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Hayes, Dorothy, 1966-71 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Kamaiko, Jack, 1974-76 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Koch, Ray and Charlotte ("Chucky"), 1962, 1969-75 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Levine, Rachel A., 1952-57 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Levine, Rachel A., 1958-61 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Levine, Rachel A., 1962-69, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Marsh, Marguerite, 1966-70, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Middleman, Ruth, 1974-76 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Reed, Mildred, 1957-77 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Van Kleeck, Mary, 1943, 1949, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Weed, Verne, 1967-74, undated (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Individual Correspondence: Outgoing
    - B-W, 1961-74 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Berkman, Tessie, 1933-39 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Berkman, Tessie, 1940-46 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Berkman, Tessie, 1950-59 (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Berkman, Tessie, 1960-75, undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Boggs, James, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Flexner, Eleanor, and Helen Terry, 1954-57 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Flexner, Eleanor, and Helen Terry, 1958-59 (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Flexner, Eleanor, and Helen Terry, 1960-61 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Flexner, Eleanor, and Helen Terry, 1962-72 (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Goleman, Fay and Judith, 1952-71 (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Harper, Ruth, 1962-66, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Koch, Ray and Charlotte, 1955-61 (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Koch, Ray and Charlotte, 1962-67 (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Koch, Ray and Charlotte, 1968-75 (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Levine, Rachel A., 1952-55 (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Levine, Rachel A., 1956-58 (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Levine, Rachel A., 1961-63 (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Levine, Rachel A., 1964-69 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Levine, Rachel A., 1971-75 (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Middleman, Ruth, 1974, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Noble, Rosel, 1959-65 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Pataki, Vivian (includes Pearl Turk, Lois, and Murray Kaufman) 1948-73, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Rabinowitz, Clar, 1944-73 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Schwarz, Ruth Newman, 1937-56 (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Stinson, Norma and Wesley, 1961-69 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence
    - Readers' comments on An Uncharted Journey, 1963-64 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Readers' comments on other works by, Bertha C. Reynolds 1932-73 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Congressmen, 1966-68 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Religion, 1931 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Religion, 1950-68 (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Professional subjects, 1939, 1951,1968-75 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Social Work Today, back issues, 1959-64, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 52)
- Series II. PROFESSIONAL ACTIVITIES 1919-1975
  - Danvers State Hospital
    - Case studies, 1922 Jan (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Smith College School for Social Work
    - Seminar on case work: notes, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 54)
    - Everett Kimball: correspondence, 1924-36 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Everett Kimball: correspondence, 1937-39 (Box 3, Folder 56)
    - Case histories, 1932, 1934 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Institute for Child Guidance
    - Attitude Study: preliminary draft, report,printed materials, 1930, undated (Box 3, Folder 58)